<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Mental health - Tag - My New Hugo Site</title>
        <link>http://example.org/tags/mental-health/</link>
        <description>Mental health - Tag - My New Hugo Site</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 14:23:26 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/tags/mental-health/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Revolutionizing Medicine: How Brain Research Can Save Lives</title>
    <link>http://example.org/posts/revolutionizing-medicine-how-brain-research-can-save-lives/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 14:23:26 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
                    <name>Wilson</name>
                </author><guid>http://example.org/posts/revolutionizing-medicine-how-brain-research-can-save-lives/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/posts/revolutionizing-medicine-how-brain-research-can-save-lives/revolutionizing-medicine-how-brain-research-can-save-lives.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><h2 id="how-biomedical-research-has-revolutionized-the-treatment-of-serious-diseases" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#how-biomedical-research-has-revolutionized-the-treatment-of-serious-diseases" class="header-mark"></a>How Biomedical Research has Revolutionized the Treatment of Serious Diseases</h2><p>Biomedical research has played a vital role in developing advanced treatments for many serious diseases, improving the quality of life of millions of people around the world. One such example is acute lymphoblastic leukemia, a type of blood cancer that primarily affects children. Thanks to significant advancements in biomedical research, the survival rates for this disease have increased from 10% in the 1960s to over 90% today.</p>
<p>Similarly, heart disease, which was once considered a death sentence, has seen significant improvements in its treatment and management due to biomedical research. The development of innovative treatments, such as statins, has helped reduce the incidence of heart attacks and other cardiovascular events. Additionally, the development of new surgical techniques, such as minimally invasive procedures, has made cardiac surgeries safer and less invasive for patients.</p>
<p>The impact of biomedical research goes beyond these two diseases. Many other serious illnesses, including cancer, HIV/AIDS, and diabetes, have seen significant improvements in their treatment and management due to the progress made in this field. Without biomedical research, many of the treatments that we take for granted today would not exist.</p>
<p>In conclusion, biomedical research has made significant contributions to the field of medicine, revolutionizing the treatment and management of many serious diseases. Continued investment in this field is crucial to developing new treatments and improving the quality of life for millions of people around the world.</p>
<h3 id="suicide-is-prevalent" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#suicide-is-prevalent" class="header-mark"></a>Suicide is prevalent</h3><p>Suicide is a serious issue that affects people of all ages and backgrounds, but it is particularly prevalent among young people in the United States. In fact, suicide is the third leading cause of death among individuals aged 15 to 25 in the US. Every year, there are approximately 38,000 suicides in the country.</p>
<p>There are many factors that can contribute to suicidal behavior, including mental illness, substance abuse, and life stressors such as relationship problems or financial difficulties. It&rsquo;s important for individuals who are struggling with suicidal thoughts to seek help from a mental health professional, a crisis hotline, or a trusted friend or family member.</p>
<p>Research has shown that prevention efforts, such as suicide hotlines and crisis intervention programs, can be effective in reducing suicide rates. Additionally, early identification and treatment of mental health issues can also help to prevent suicidal behavior.</p>
<h3 id="mental-disorders-are-brain-disorders" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#mental-disorders-are-brain-disorders" class="header-mark"></a>Mental disorders are brain disorders</h3><p>Mental disorders such as depression, anxiety, and bipolar disorder affect millions of people worldwide. In the past, these disorders were viewed as purely psychological, but recent research suggests that they are brain disorders. By examining the brain activity and structure of people with mental disorders, researchers have discovered that there are significant differences in the brains of those with mental disorders compared to those without. This has led to a shift in how mental disorders are viewed and treated.</p>
<p>The concept of mental disorders as brain disorders helps reduce the stigma associated with these conditions and allows for more effective treatments. It also provides hope for those living with mental disorders, as it shows that progress is being made in understanding and treating these conditions. By continuing to study the brain and its functions, researchers hope to develop better treatments and even cures for mental disorders in the future.</p>
<h2 id="brain-disorders-have-predictable-patterns" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#brain-disorders-have-predictable-patterns" class="header-mark"></a>Brain Disorders have Predictable Patterns</h2><p>The way the brain is wired for people with brain disorders like depression and obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) can be predictable. This means that by identifying and understanding these patterns, researchers can develop better treatments for these conditions. For instance, researchers have found that the brains of people with OCD have hyperactive circuits that control worry and fear. Understanding this pattern has led to new treatments that can target those circuits to help alleviate symptoms.</p>
<p>Similarly, research has shown that the brains of people with depression have decreased activity in certain areas that are responsible for regulating mood. By identifying these patterns, scientists have been able to develop new treatments that can stimulate activity in those areas to improve mood. This approach has led to the development of treatments like transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS), which uses magnetic fields to stimulate activity in the brain.</p>
<p>Overall, by identifying and understanding the predictable patterns in the brain associated with certain disorders, researchers can develop more effective treatments to help people with these conditions.</p>
<h3 id="schizophrenia-as-a-brain-disorder" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#schizophrenia-as-a-brain-disorder" class="header-mark"></a>Schizophrenia as a brain disorder</h3><p>Schizophrenia is a serious brain disorder that affects approximately 1% of the world&rsquo;s population. It is a chronic condition that typically develops in early adulthood and can cause symptoms such as delusions, hallucinations, and disordered thinking. While the exact cause of schizophrenia is not yet known, it is clear that the brain is affected much earlier than behavioral symptoms emerge. This means that detecting brain changes early can lead to early intervention, which is crucial for improving outcomes.</p>
<p>Biomedical research has led to significant progress in understanding the brain mechanisms underlying schizophrenia. For instance, researchers have identified specific brain regions and circuits that are involved in the disorder. They have also discovered genetic variations that increase the risk of developing schizophrenia. Additionally, advances in brain imaging technology have made it possible to detect subtle changes in brain structure and function in people with schizophrenia, which can aid in diagnosis and treatment.</p>
<p>Overall, by recognizing schizophrenia as a brain disorder, researchers and clinicians can better understand its underlying mechanisms and develop more effective interventions. Early detection and treatment of brain changes associated with schizophrenia can help to improve outcomes for people living with this condition.</p>
<h3 id="early-detection-is-key" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#early-detection-is-key" class="header-mark"></a>Early detection is key</h3><p>The earlier a disease or disorder is detected, the better the outcomes for patients. This is particularly true for brain disorders, where changes in the brain can occur long before behavioral symptoms emerge. For example, detecting changes in the brain of a person with schizophrenia can lead to early intervention and treatment, improving the chances of recovery. Similarly, identifying risk factors for suicide and intervening early can save lives. There are many success stories in medicine that demonstrate the importance of early detection and intervention, highlighting the need for continued research in this area.</p>
<h2 id="tools-for-detecting-brain-changes-are-improving" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#tools-for-detecting-brain-changes-are-improving" class="header-mark"></a>Tools for detecting brain changes are improving</h2><p>The field of neuroscience is rapidly advancing, and new technologies are emerging that can detect brain changes much earlier than ever before. These tools have the potential to revolutionize our understanding of brain disorders like schizophrenia and depression, which can lead to earlier detection and intervention. Some of the technologies being developed include magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), positron emission tomography (PET), and electroencephalography (EEG). While these technologies are not yet perfect, they offer promising new avenues for research and treatment. As these tools continue to improve, we can hope for even more accurate and effective interventions for brain disorders.</p>
<h3 id="changes-in-concepts-and-technology" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#changes-in-concepts-and-technology" class="header-mark"></a>Changes in concepts and technology</h3><p>The video also highlights how we often overestimate the change that will happen in the short term and underestimate the change that will happen in the long term. While we&rsquo;ve made incredible strides in biomedical research and mental health treatment, there&rsquo;s still much more to learn and discover. New technologies are emerging that allow us to detect brain changes much earlier than before, and there&rsquo;s a growing understanding that mental disorders are brain disorders that require early intervention. In the next few years, we may see new breakthroughs that can revolutionize the way we diagnose and treat mental illness, but we must remain patient and continue to invest in research and development. In the long term, the possibilities are endless, and we may eventually see a world where mental illness is as treatable and manageable as physical illness.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#conclusion" class="header-mark"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>In conclusion, biomedical research has been instrumental in saving lives and improving outcomes for many serious diseases, such as acute lymphoblastic leukemia and heart disease. Suicide is a prevalent issue, with 38,000 suicides each year in the United States alone, making it the third most common cause of death among people between the ages of 15 and 25. It&rsquo;s time to rethink mental disorders as brain disorders to make progress in understanding and treating them. Brain disorders, such as depression and obsessive-compulsive disorder, have predictable patterns, and detecting brain changes early can lead to early intervention, which can significantly improve outcomes for patients. Schizophrenia is a disorder that affects the brain much earlier than the behavioral symptoms emerge, highlighting the importance of early detection and intervention.</p>
<p>The good news stories in medicine are all about early detection and intervention, and new technologies are emerging that allow us to detect brain changes much earlier than before. While we may overestimate the changes that will occur in the next two years, we often underestimate the change that will happen in the next ten years. It&rsquo;s exciting to think about the potential for advances in biomedical research to continue to improve health outcomes and save lives.</p>
<p>Overall, the progress made in biomedical research is remarkable, and it&rsquo;s critical to continue investing in this area to continue making significant strides in medicine. Through research and development, we can gain a better understanding of diseases and find innovative ways to diagnose and treat them, ultimately leading to improved patient outcomes and better quality of life for all.</p>
]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Rewiring the Brain: How Social Connection and Neuroplasticity Can Combat Addiction and Compulsive Behaviors</title>
    <link>http://example.org/posts/rewiring-the-brain-how-social-connection-and-neuroplasticity-can-combat/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 18:31:09 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
                    <name>Jane</name>
                </author><guid>http://example.org/posts/rewiring-the-brain-how-social-connection-and-neuroplasticity-can-combat/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/posts/rewiring-the-brain-how-social-connection-and-neuroplasticity-can-combat/rewiring-the-brain-how-social-connection-and-neuroplasticity-can-combat.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><h2 id="understanding-the-spectrum-of-human-experience" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#understanding-the-spectrum-of-human-experience" class="header-mark"></a>Understanding the Spectrum of Human Experience</h2><p>Have you ever wondered what it means to be normal or sick? These are questions that have puzzled people for centuries. In this blog post, we will explore the spectrum of human experience and how it relates to involuntary movements, such as those experienced by people with Tourette&rsquo;s syndrome. We will also examine the brain&rsquo;s default state, which is often described as being on autopilot.</p>
<h3 id="tourettes-syndrome-and-involuntary-movements" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#tourettes-syndrome-and-involuntary-movements" class="header-mark"></a>Tourette&rsquo;s Syndrome and Involuntary Movements</h3><p>Tourette&rsquo;s syndrome is a neurological disorder characterized by stereotyped movements called tics. These tics are involuntary in the sense that they occur without any conscious attention or intention. People with Tourette&rsquo;s often describe feeling an uncomfortable sensation called a premonitory urge right before a tic happens, particularly when they are trying to resist it. While tics and blinking are not the same neurologically speaking, the experience of premonitory urges is relatable to anyone who has experienced a similar feeling.</p>
<h3 id="the-brains-default-state-autopilot" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-brains-default-state-autopilot" class="header-mark"></a>The Brain&rsquo;s Default State: Autopilot</h3><p>The brain&rsquo;s default state is often compared to a car idling in drive rather than being parked. Some of what we think we choose to do is actually a result of habits and programming. The striatum, a structure in the brain, detects emotional and sensory-motor conditions and triggers the behavior that we have done most often in the past under those same conditions. This is why some people describe their brain as running on autopilot.</p>
<p>It is important to note that the brain&rsquo;s autopilot is not always a bad thing. In fact, it can be very helpful for tasks that we do repeatedly, such as driving or typing. However, when it comes to compulsive behaviors, the brain&rsquo;s autopilot can be a problem. When we engage in behaviors that are coerced by uncomfortable urges we cannot consciously resist, we may be experiencing compulsive behaviors. Miswiring in the striatum has been linked to compulsive behaviors, and it is an area of research that is still being explored.</p>
<p>In conclusion, understanding the spectrum of human experience is essential for understanding involuntary movements, such as those experienced by people with Tourette&rsquo;s syndrome. It is also important to recognize the brain&rsquo;s default state and how it relates to compulsive behaviors. By understanding these concepts, we can work towards a better understanding of the human brain and its complexities.</p>
<h2 id="compulsive-behaviors-and-miswiring-in-the-striatum" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#compulsive-behaviors-and-miswiring-in-the-striatum" class="header-mark"></a>Compulsive Behaviors and Miswiring in the Striatum</h2><p>The striatum is a structure in the brain that is responsible for triggering behaviors that we have done most often in the past under the same conditions. Miswiring in the striatum can lead to compulsive behaviors, which are behaviors that are coerced by uncomfortable urges that cannot be consciously resisted.</p>
<p>Compulsive behaviors can be seen in people with neurological disorders such as Tourette&rsquo;s syndrome, as well as in addiction. Studies have shown that the effects of addictive drugs and the effects of abnormal neurotransmission on involuntary movements and compulsive behaviors all converge in the striatum.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the striatum has also been linked to social neuroscience. Social neurochemistry in the striatum is linked to things like oxytocin, which is the hormone that makes cuddling feel warm and fuzzy. The striatum is also implicated in signaling at opioid receptors.</p>
<p>Loneliness is a significant danger that acts through the brain&rsquo;s reward system to make the state of affairs literally painful. When we don&rsquo;t have enough signaling at opioid receptors, we can feel alone in a room full of people we care about and love. Social isolation acts through receptors for naturally occurring opioids and other social neurotransmitters to leave the striatum in a state where its response to things that signal reward and pleasure is completely over the top. In this state of hypersensitivity, our brains signal deep dissatisfaction. We become restless, irritable, and impulsive.</p>
<p>The areas in the country that are most economically hard-hit, where people feel most desolate about their life&rsquo;s meaning, are also the places where there have been communities most ravaged by opioids. It&rsquo;s possible to rewire and reprogram the autopilot that runs our behaviors on habit in the striatum through neuroplasticity. However, it involves neuroplasticity to learn new things.</p>
<p>Social impulses need to replace drug-cued compulsive behaviors because we need to rebalance neurochemically our social reward system. One possibility is to create and study scalable tools for people to connect with one another over a mutual interest in recovery through psycho-spiritual practices.</p>
<p>In conclusion, compulsive behaviors and miswiring in the striatum are linked to social neuroscience and the danger of social disconnection and loneliness. It&rsquo;s essential to understand the spectrum of human experience and remove the otherness of people who struggle with self-destruction.</p>
<h2 id="the-link-between-social-isolation-and-opioid-addiction" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-link-between-social-isolation-and-opioid-addiction" class="header-mark"></a>The Link Between Social Isolation and Opioid Addiction</h2><p>The opioid crisis and epidemic is out of control, with 91 people dying every day in the United States from overdose. Between 2002 and 2015, the number of deaths from heroin increased by a factor of six. Despite this, the way we treat addiction isn&rsquo;t working, at least not for everyone. Studies show that relapse rates among heroin users exceed 50% within the first week and are about 80% within the first month.</p>
<p>While addiction is a brain-based disease state, how we relate to that disease makes an enormous difference in how we treat people with addictions. Social isolation and disconnection play a significant role in addiction, making it much harder to recover. Social isolation acts through the brain&rsquo;s reward system to make this state of affairs literally painful. Loneliness is very dangerous and increases the risk of early death, even more than chronic excessive alcohol consumption. It also predisposes people to entire spectrums of physical and mental illnesses.</p>
<p>The Link Between Social Isolation and Opioid Addiction suggests that people who tend to avoid relapse tend to be those who have broad reciprocal social relationships, where they can be of service to each other and help. Being of service allows people to connect, and if they can&rsquo;t authentically connect, society increasingly lacks the ability to experience things that are transcendent and beyond ourselves. The hunger created in the brain by loneliness hypersensitizes neurochemically our reward system, and social isolation acts through receptors for naturally occurring opioids and other social neurotransmitters to leave the striatum in a state where its response to things that signal reward and pleasure is completely over the top. In this state of hypersensitivity, our brains signal deep dissatisfaction, making us restless, irritable, and impulsive.</p>
<h2 id="hope-through-neuroplasticity" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#hope-through-neuroplasticity" class="header-mark"></a>Hope through Neuroplasticity</h2><p>Neuroplasticity is the ability of the brain to reprogram and rewire itself, allowing us to learn new things. The striatum is our autopilot running our behaviors on habit, and it&rsquo;s possible to rewire and reprogram that autopilot, but it involves neuroplasticity. We need neuronally firing repeated experiences in order for the striatum to undergo that necessary neuroplasticity that allows it to take that &ldquo;Go find heroin&rdquo; autopilot offline.</p>
<p>With the convergence of social neuroscience, addiction, and compulsive spectrum disorders in the striatum, it suggests that it&rsquo;s not simply enough to teach the striatum healthier responses to compulsive urges. We need social impulses to replace drug-cued compulsive behaviors because we need to rebalance neurochemically our social reward system. Unless that happens, we&rsquo;re going to be left in a state of craving, no matter what besides our drug we repeatedly practice doing.</p>
<p>Hope through neuroplasticity comes from the fact that it&rsquo;s possible to rewire our brains to replace destructive, compulsive behaviors with healthy, social connective behaviors. This involves practicing social connective behaviors instead of compulsive behaviors when we&rsquo;re lonely, when we are cued to remember our drug. When we connect around what&rsquo;s broken, we connect as human beings, and we heal ourselves from the compulsive self-destruction that was our response to the pain of disconnection.</p>
<h2 id="the-importance-of-social-connective-behaviors" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-importance-of-social-connective-behaviors" class="header-mark"></a>The Importance of Social Connective Behaviors</h2><p>Social media can&rsquo;t go deep enough for this; it doesn&rsquo;t encourage us to share but rather to compare. Studies show that people actually tend to feel more isolated from social media. The difference between having superficial small talk with someone and an authentic, deeply connected conversation with eye contact is vast. Stigma keeps us separate and keeps us sick, and it often makes it safer for addicts to connect with other addicts</p>
<h2 id="the-limits-of-social-media-in-addressing-addiction" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-limits-of-social-media-in-addressing-addiction" class="header-mark"></a>The Limits of Social Media in Addressing Addiction</h2><p>Social media has become a ubiquitous part of our daily lives. It allows us to connect with friends and family, share our experiences, and even find support for issues we&rsquo;re facing. However, when it comes to addressing addiction, social media may have its limitations.</p>
<p>In the midst of the opioid crisis, many people turn to social media for support and information. There are countless groups and pages dedicated to addiction recovery, and people share their stories and struggles openly. While this can be a helpful tool for some, it&rsquo;s important to recognize the limitations.</p>
<p>One of the main issues with social media is that it often encourages comparison rather than connection. People may see others in recovery who seem to be doing better than them, which can lead to feelings of inadequacy and shame. Additionally, social media can be a superficial way of connecting, lacking the depth and authenticity that true human connection provides.</p>
<p>Stigma is another issue that can limit the effectiveness of social media in addressing addiction. Addiction is still often viewed as a moral failing rather than a medical condition, and people who struggle with addiction can be met with judgment and condemnation. This stigma can make it difficult for people to reach out for help and can lead to social isolation.</p>
<p>Removing stigma and connecting as human beings is essential to addressing addiction. When we see addiction as part of the spectrum of human experience, we remove the otherness of people who struggle with addiction. We create a space for connection and healing.</p>
<p>This is where seeking healing together for all struggles with humanness comes into play. When we connect around what&rsquo;s broken, we connect as human beings. We remove the stigma between doctors and patients and caregivers. We put the question of what it means to be normal versus sick back on the spectrum of the human condition.</p>
<p>While social media can play a role in addressing addiction, it&rsquo;s important to recognize its limitations. To truly address addiction and promote healing, we must move beyond superficial connections and remove the stigma that keeps us separate. By connecting as human beings and seeking healing together, we can create a space for true recovery and growth.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#conclusion" class="header-mark"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>The opioid crisis has brought attention to the urgent need to address addiction and its underlying causes. As we have seen, addiction is not simply a matter of choice or willpower, but a complex interplay of neurobiology, social factors, and personal experiences. The striatum, a brain structure involved in reward and habit formation, has been implicated in both compulsive behaviors and social connection. Social isolation and loneliness have been linked to addiction, while social connective behaviors may hold the key to recovery.</p>
<p>However, social media and stigma can create barriers to authentic social connection and prevent individuals from seeking help. It is essential to view addiction and mental health struggles as part of the spectrum of human experience, removing the otherness and stigma that can prevent individuals from seeking the help they need. Seeking healing together as human beings, through scalable tools and interventions that promote social connective behaviors, offers hope for addressing addiction and promoting mental health and wellbeing.</p>
<p>Ultimately, by recognizing the limits of current approaches and embracing a more holistic understanding of addiction and the human experience, we can create a more compassionate and effective response to the opioid crisis and other mental health challenges.</p>
]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>The Science of Building Inner Strength: Turning Passing Experiences into Lasting Structure</title>
    <link>http://example.org/posts/science-of-building-inner-strength-turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 12:46:06 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
                    <name>Emily</name>
                </author><guid>http://example.org/posts/science-of-building-inner-strength-turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/posts/science-of-building-inner-strength-turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting/science-of-building-inner-strength-turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><h2 id="introduction-a-simple-yet-powerful-method-grounded-in-neuroscience" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#introduction-a-simple-yet-powerful-method-grounded-in-neuroscience" class="header-mark"></a>Introduction: A Simple Yet Powerful Method Grounded in Neuroscience</h2><p>Our brain is a complex organ responsible for regulating our thoughts, emotions, and behaviors. But what if we told you that there&rsquo;s a simple yet powerful method to help turn passing experiences into lasting structure within the brain? In this blog post, we&rsquo;ll explore the neuroscience behind this method and how it can help us build inner strengths such as happiness, resilience, and confidence.</p>
<h3 id="overcoming-negative-experiences-and-hardwired-negativity-bias" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#overcoming-negative-experiences-and-hardwired-negativity-bias" class="header-mark"></a>Overcoming Negative Experiences and Hardwired Negativity Bias</h3><p>We&rsquo;ve all experienced negative events in our lives that leave a lasting impact on our psyche. Unfortunately, our brains are hardwired with a negativity bias, meaning we&rsquo;re more likely to remember negative experiences than positive ones. This can make it difficult to build inner strengths and cope with hard things.</p>
<p>However, there is a way to overcome this hardwired negativity bias by learning how to take in the good. By focusing on positive experiences and staying with them for a longer period of time, we can gradually weave them into the fabric of our brain and create a more positive outlook on life.</p>
<h3 id="how-positive-experiences-are-built-from-wholesome-qualities" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#how-positive-experiences-are-built-from-wholesome-qualities" class="header-mark"></a>How Positive Experiences are Built from Wholesome Qualities</h3><p>Many of the inner strengths we desire, such as happiness, confidence, and love, are built from positive experiences of those strengths. For example, if we want to feel more confident, we need to have more experiences of accomplishment or coping.</p>
<p>However, the problem lies in the fact that our brains are more likely to remember negative experiences than positive ones. This means that we need to intentionally focus on positive experiences and learn how to take them in, so they become lasting neural traits in our brains.</p>
<p>In the next section of this blog post, we&rsquo;ll dive deeper into the steps of taking in the good and how it can help us build inner strengths in the brain.</p>
<h2 id="the-importance-of-building-inner-strengths-in-the-brain" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-importance-of-building-inner-strengths-in-the-brain" class="header-mark"></a>The Importance of Building Inner Strengths in the Brain</h2><p>The human brain is a remarkable organ capable of change and growth throughout our lives. This is especially true for our inner strengths, such as happiness, resilience, and positive emotion. In this blog post, we&rsquo;ll explore the importance of building these inner strengths in the brain and how neuroscience has shown that mental activity can change brain structure.</p>
<p>Neurons that fire together wire together, which means that passing mental states become lasting neural traits. Bit by bit, we can actually weave resources into the fabric of our brain and, therefore, our life. The challenge is how to get these experiences into our brain when the brain has a hardwired negativity bias. This negativity bias means that the brain is very good at learning from bad experiences, but bad at learning from good ones.</p>
<p>To overcome this bottleneck in the brain, we need to learn to take in the good, which means we need to pop open this bottleneck in the brain and gradually weave good experiences into the fabric of our brain and our life. We need to have a good experience, enrich the experience, absorb it, and, if we like, link it with something negative.</p>
<p>Neuroscience has shown us that mental activity can change brain structure. For example, taxi cab drivers in London have a thicker brain in a key part called the hippocampus that does visual-spatial memory. Meanwhile, the experience of stress releases cortisol in the body, which goes up into the brain and gradually stimulates the alarm bell of the brain, the amygdala. This creates a negative feedback loop where cortisol weakens, and it actually kills neurons in the hippocampus, which, besides doing visual-spatial memory, calms down the amygdala and stress altogether. This means that the mental experience of stress, especially if it&rsquo;s chronic and moderate to severe, gradually changes the structure of the brain so that we become progressively more sensitive to stress.</p>
<p>This understanding of how mental activity changes brain structure is valuable because the inner strengths that we all want are built out of the brain. If we want to feel more confident, for example, we need to have more experiences of accomplishment or coping. If we want to have a more loving heart, we need to practice more moments of compassion or kindness for others.</p>
<p>In conclusion, building inner strengths in the brain is important for our overall well-being and happiness. We can change our brain structure by taking in the good, allowing ourselves to have positive experiences, enriching those experiences, absorbing them, and linking them with negative experiences. By doing this, we can gradually build up our inner strengths, making us more resilient and better able to cope with life&rsquo;s challenges.</p>
<h2 id="turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting-structure" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#turning-passing-experiences-into-lasting-structure" class="header-mark"></a>Turning Passing Experiences into Lasting Structure</h2><p>Our brains are wired to pay more attention to negative experiences than positive ones. This tendency is known as the negativity bias, and it can create a bottleneck in the brain that makes it difficult to build inner strengths such as resilience, happiness, and love. However, with the right approach, we can turn passing experiences into lasting structures in the brain.</p>
<h3 id="the-four-steps-to-taking-in-the-good" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-four-steps-to-taking-in-the-good" class="header-mark"></a>The Four Steps to Taking in the Good</h3><p>According to neuropsychologist Rick Hanson, there are four simple steps to taking in the good:</p>
<h4 id="1-have-a-good-experience" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#1-have-a-good-experience" class="header-mark"></a>1. Have a good experience.</h4><p>The first step is to have a good experience. This means actively seeking out positive experiences or being mindful of them when they happen.</p>
<h4 id="2-enrich-the-experience" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#2-enrich-the-experience" class="header-mark"></a>2. Enrich the experience.</h4><p>Once you have a good experience, the second step is to enrich it. This means savoring the experience and helping it become more intense and vivid.</p>
<h4 id="3-absorb-the-experience" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#3-absorb-the-experience" class="header-mark"></a>3. Absorb the experience.</h4><p>The third step is to absorb the experience. This means focusing on the experience and intending for it to sink into your brain and become a lasting neural trait.</p>
<h4 id="4-link-positive-and-negative-experiences-optional" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#4-link-positive-and-negative-experiences-optional" class="header-mark"></a>4. Link positive and negative experiences (optional).</h4><p>The final step is optional, but it can be particularly helpful in overcoming negative experiences. This step involves linking positive experiences with negative ones, so that the positive experience can soothe or even replace the negative one.</p>
<h3 id="linking-positive-and-negative-experiences" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#linking-positive-and-negative-experiences" class="header-mark"></a>Linking Positive and Negative Experiences</h3><p>Linking positive and negative experiences is a powerful technique for healing old pain or neglect. It involves intentionally recalling a positive experience while also acknowledging a negative one. This allows the positive experience to soothe or even replace the negative one over time.</p>
<p>For example, if you have a negative memory from childhood, you can recall a positive experience from around the same time period and focus on both simultaneously. This can help rewire your brain to associate positive experiences with negative ones, making it easier to cope with difficult emotions and memories.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#conclusion" class="header-mark"></a>Conclusion</h3><p>By following the four steps to taking in the good and linking positive and negative experiences, we can gradually build inner strengths in our brains that will help us cope with life&rsquo;s challenges. It&rsquo;s not about ignoring negative experiences or pretending everything is okay. It&rsquo;s about intentionally focusing on the good and allowing it to sink into our brains and become a lasting part of who we are. With practice, we can turn passing experiences into lasting structures and build the inner strengths we need to live a happy, fulfilling life.</p>
<h2 id="applying-the-method-to-heal-pain-and-neglect" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#applying-the-method-to-heal-pain-and-neglect" class="header-mark"></a>Applying the Method to Heal Pain and Neglect</h2><p>The method of taking in the good, as we have seen, is a simple yet powerful tool that helps build inner strengths in the brain. It involves actively noticing and holding onto positive experiences for a few seconds longer than usual, enriching them, absorbing them, and optionally linking them to negative experiences to soothe and ease them. But this method is not just for building inner strengths. It can also be applied to heal pain and neglect.</p>
<p>As we have seen, the brain is wired to pay more attention to negative experiences than positive ones. This is because negative experiences are usually more salient and have more immediate consequences for our survival. However, this negativity bias can create a bottleneck in our brain, making it harder for us to build inner strengths or heal from past pain and neglect.</p>
<p>But by taking in the good, we can gradually change the structure of our brain and build resilience, happiness, and other inner strengths. We can also heal old pain and neglect by linking positive experiences with negative ones. For example, if we have experienced neglect in our childhood, we can consciously focus on positive experiences of feeling cared for and loved, and link them to the negative experiences of neglect. This can help us gradually heal from the wounds of the past and build inner strengths that we may have missed out on in childhood.</p>
<p>The law of little things tells us that it is the accumulation of small positive experiences that can make a big difference in our lives. By taking in the good regularly, even in small doses, we can gradually build a reservoir of inner strengths that can help us cope with life&rsquo;s challenges and have more to give to others.</p>
<p>The most important minute in our life is the next one. By consciously taking in the good in each moment, we can gradually transform our brain and our life. We can become more resilient, happier, and more compassionate, not just towards ourselves but towards others as well.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the method of taking in the good is a simple yet powerful tool that can help us build inner strengths, heal from past pain and neglect, and transform our brain and our life. By applying this method to our daily life, we can gradually accumulate small positive experiences that can make a big difference in our well-being and our relationships with others.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-1" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#conclusion-1" class="header-mark"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>In conclusion, building inner strengths in the brain is crucial for living a happy and fulfilling life. Neuroscience shows us that mental activity can change brain structure, and we can use this knowledge to our advantage by taking in the good and turning passing experiences into lasting structure. The hardwired negativity bias of the brain creates a fundamental bottleneck that we need to overcome in order to build positive experiences into our brain. The four steps of taking in the good - having it, enriching the experience, absorbing it, and linking it with negative experiences if necessary - can help us overcome this bottleneck and build the inner strengths we desire.</p>
<p>Moreover, this method is not just limited to creating happiness and resilience, but it can also be used to heal old pain and neglect. The law of little things emphasizes that it is the accumulation of little good things that take us to a better place, and we need to take control of the most important minute in our lives by actively seeking out and enjoying the good that is available to us.</p>
<p>Overall, building inner strengths in the brain is a gradual process that requires patience and dedication, but the rewards are well worth it. By taking in the good and building positive experiences into our brain, we can become more confident, loving, and resilient individuals who are better equipped to cope with life&rsquo;s challenges and give back to those around us.</p>
]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
